A Guide to the Mary Goins Roots Collection, 1858-2017
Virginia Room, Fairfax County Public Library
The Mary Goins Roots Collection, 1858-2017
Fairfax County Public Library
MSS 07-26
8.5 linear feet
The Mary Goins Roots Collection consists of 8.5 linear feet and spans the years 1858-2017 and consists of family papers, correspondence, programs, yearbooks, awards and certificates, vital records, newspaper articles, identification badges and cards, obituaries, photographs, photo albums, a scrapbook, property records, yearbooks, and other school ephemera.
Roots, Mary Goins (1939-2017)
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
None
Acquisition Information
Donated by Daphne Roots in August 2018 and July 2021
Historical and Biographical Information
Mary Katherine Goins was born on April 22, 1939, to Annie and James M. Goins in Fairfax, Virginia. She grew up in Sideburn, Virginia, graduated from Luther Jackson High School in 1957, and attended St. Paul’s College where she met her husband William Thomas Roots. After graduating in 1961, she and Roots married in November 1961 at Little Zion Baptist Church in Burke.
She began her thirty-two-year teaching career with Fairfax County Public Schools in 1961, first teaching at Eleven Oaks Elementary School in Fairfax. In 1978, she received a Masters in Education from George Mason University and went on to serve as a human relations officer, vice-principal, and principal at several Fairfax County elementary schools until retiring in 1993. She came out of retirement to serve as a principal for Charles County Public Schools in Maryland for another six years. In 1998, she earned the Washington Post Distinguished Educator Award for her time at Eva Turner Elementary School in Waldorf, Maryland.
Her husband, William T. Roots, died on March 12, 2016. Mary Roots passed away at age 78 in Woodbridge, Virginia on October 21, 2017. They are both buried in the family burial ground at the Jack and Lizzy Pearson Cemetery in Burke, Virginia.
Scope and Content
The Mary Goins Roots Collection consists of 8.5 linear feet and spans the years 1858-2017 and consists of family papers, correspondence, programs, yearbooks, awards and certificates, vital records, newspaper articles, identification badges and cards, obituaries, photographs, photo albums, a scrapbook, property records, yearbooks, and other school ephemera. Subjects covered are Mary Goins Roots, her family, and her ancestors including the Coffer, Goins, Jeffrey, Pearson and Wright families, the Sideburn Civic Association, Greater Little Zion Baptist Church, and Fairfax County Public Schools, and Charles County Public Schools.
Series 1: Mary Goins Roots, 1954-2017, Boxes 1-4 and 13
Arranged alphabetically, this series contains personal records for Mary Goins Roots. Included are awards and certificates, correspondence, documents, by-laws, resumes, newspaper articles, yearbooks, programs, photographs, family genealogy notes, an identification card, and an embroidered patch. Subjects primarily consist of Roots’ education at St. Paul’s College and George Mason University, and her career with Fairfax County and Charles County Public Schools.
Series 2: William T. Roots, 1951-2016, Box 4
Arranged alphabetically, this series contains materials from Mary Goins Roots’ husband, William T. Roots. Included are awards and certificates, correspondence, papers, military records, photographs, and a student identification badge from St. Paul’s College. Subjects covered are Roots’ education including certificates from Concord School in Roseville, Virginia; Walker-Grant Elementary School in Fredericksburg, Virginia; and Walker-Grant High School. Documents also pertain to Roots’ career with the United States Air Force; Giant Food; the Engineering and Maintenance Division at National Airport; and Prince William County Crossing Guard Bureau.
Series 3: Coffer, Goins, Jeffrey, Pearson, and Wright Families, 1915-2011, Boxes 4-5
Arranged alphabetically by name, this series includes documents from Mary Goins Roots’ ancestors and relatives consisting of the Coffer, Goins, Jeffrey, Pearson, and Wright families. Included are vital records, death certificates, obituaries, funeral programs and guest books, correspondence, certificates and awards, newspaper articles, identification cards, and a report card. Of particular note are materials from James M. Goins, Mary Roots’ father and known locally as “The Godfather of Zion Drive”. As a community leader he was instrumental in bringing improvements to the Sideburn, Virginia community including sewer and water hook-ups, the David R. Pinn Memorial Civic and Recreation Center, recreational facilities, and the Goins Manor subdivision.
Series 4: Property Records, 1969-2012, Box 6
Arranged alphabetically, this series contains property records from the Roots, Goins, Jeffrey, and Wright families. Included are correspondence, deeds, and legal and financial records.
Series 5: Sideburn Civic Association, 1963-1989, Box 7
Arranged alphabetically, this series includes bylaws, correspondence, programs, financial information, photographs, speeches, and other paperwork relating to the Sideburn Civic Association. Mary Roots’ father, James M. Goins was the group’s president. The Black non-profit civic association was formed with the purpose to upgrade the community of Sideburn, provide recreational facilities, and promote and protect the civic and community interests of its residents. Documents in this series cover activities of the group including annual dinners and the David R. Pinn Memorial Civic and Recreation Center.
Series 6: Noble Lodge No. 9627 Grand United Order of Odd Fellows of America, 1921-1922, Box 7
This series contains correspondence and fundraising paperwork for the construction of an Odd Fellows Hall in Sideburn, Virginia. Established on August 14, 1915, the Noble Lodge No. 9627 Grand United Order of Odd Fellows of America was based in Sideburn, Virginia. Fundraising paperwork includes signed pledges by those supporting the construction of the hall.
Series 7: Church Activities, 1956-2016, Box 8
Arranged alphabetically, this series contains church directories, histories, program booklets, funeral programs, and newspaper clippings. Mary Roots and her family were long-time members of Greater Little Zion Baptist Church in Burke, Virginia.
Series 8: Publications, 1858-1946, Boxes 9 and 12
Arranged chronologically, this series contains a book and periodicals collected by the family. Of particular note is a 1941 booklet commemorating the Fairfax County Colored Citizens Association's 13th anniversary which provides a detailed history and timeline of their accomplishments.
Series 9: Photographs and Albums, 1935-2011, Boxes 5-10
Arranged alphabetically, this series contains photographs, photo albums, paintings, drawings, and a photo scrapbook. Images depict Mary Goins Roots’ family, ancestors, and friends, Fairfax County and Charles County Public Schools, Greater Little Zion Baptist Church, and Sideburn, Virginia. Most of the photographs depict individuals, events, farms, and houses. Many photographs are unidentified.
Adjunct Descriptive Data
None
Financial and private documents were discarded. Willow Springs Elementary and Greenbriar West Elementary School yearbooks were removed and added to the Virginia Room’s yearbook collection.
Index Terms
African Americans -- Virginia -- Fairfax County - History; Burke (Va.) - History; Goins family; Goins, James Milton (1918-1990); Jeffrey family; Pearson family; Roots family; Roots, Mary Goins (1939-2017); Roots, William Thomas (1938-2016); Sideburn (Va.) - History; Sideburn Civic Association; Wright family
Container List
- Series 1: Mary Goins Roots, 1954-2017
  - Awards and Certificates, 1958-2002
  - Charles County Public Schools Correspondence, 1996-1999
  - Coffer Historical Exploration Society, 2014-2015
  - Eleven Oaks Elementary School (Fairfax, VA) contract (1st contract with FCPS), 1961 August
  - Eleven Oaks Elementary School (Fairfax, VA) dedication program, 1954 April 11
  - Eva Turner Elementary School (Waldorf, MD) yearbook, 1997
  - Eva Turner Elementary School (Waldorf, MD) yearbook, 1998
  - Fairfax County Alliance of Black School Educators - Constitution and By-laws, Undated
  - Fairfax County Public Schools Badge, Undated
  - Fairfax County Public Schools Correspondence, 1979-1994
  - Family Genealogy Notebook, 1956-1977
  - Family Genealogy Notes, 1995
  - Funeral, 2017
  - George Mason University commencement program, 1977 August 6
  - George Mason University Masters of Education certificate, 1977
  - News Articles, 1960-2003
  - Recertification, 1985-1993
  - Resume, Undated
  - St. Paul's College (Lawrenceville, VA) - Embroidered patch, Undated
  - St. Paul's College (Lawrenceville, VA) - Founder's Day, 1994
  - St. Paul's College (Lawrenceville, VA) - "Tiger" yearbook, 1959
  - St. Paul's College (Lawrenceville, VA) - "Tiger" yearbook, 1961
  - Washington Post Distinguished Educational Leadership Award nominations and correspondence, 1998
  - Washington Post Distinguished Educational Leadership Award correspondence and photos, 1998-1999
  - Willow Springs Elementary School retirement letters, 1994
- Series 2: William T. Roots, 1951-2016
  - Awards and Certificates, 1951-1995
  - Death, 2016
  - Prince William County Crossing Guard Bureau, 2001-2008
  - St. Paul's College (Lawrenceville, VA) - student identification card, Undated
  - United States Air Force, 1963-1969
- Series 3: Coffer, Goins, Jeffrey, Pearson, and Wright Families, 1915-2011
  - Janie Coffer Dennis, 1979-1983
  - Goins Family, 2008-2011
  - Annie V. Goins, 1981-1990
  - Annie V. Goins - Death, 1991
  - Isaac S. Goins, 1977
  - Isaac Samuel Goins, 1959-2011
  - James M. Goins, 1940-1990
  - James M. Goins - Death, 1990-1991
  - Loretta Goins [Jenny Dean High School Jay Dee yearbook], 1950
  - Pollie Goins, 1963
  - Honesty Family [cassette tape interview with Mable and Francis H. Honesty], 1976
  - Jeffrey Family, 1993-2009
  - Annie Virginia Jeffrey, 1915-1930
  - Mary Belle Pearson Jeffrey, 1954-1973
  - Thomas Jeffrey Sr., 1963-1983
  - Pearson Family, 1956-1998
  - Pearson Family - Cemetery, 1991-1992
  - Roots Family, 1989-2004
  - Willie Walton, 1975
  - Wright Family, 1983-2006
  - Edward Wright [Fairfax Elementary School report card], 1947-1948
- Series 4: Property Records, 1969-2012
  - Goins v. Wright - Jeffrey Property, 1969-1987
  - Lee Chapel Road, 1985
  - 244 Washington Street, Falmouth, VA, 2004-2007
  - 10133 Zion Drive, 1980-2012
  - 10133 Zion Drive - Van Metre Land Acquisition, 1992-2006
  - 10332 Zion Drive - Eviction, 2002
- Series 5: Sideburn Civic Association, 1963-1989
  - Sideburn Civic Association - Agreements, 1972-1986
  - Sideburn Civic Association - Annual Dinner [photos], 1975-1984
  - Sideburn Civic Association - Articles of Incorporation, Undated
  - Sideburn Civic Association - Bank Statements and Cashed Checks, 1986-1989
  - Sideburn Civic Association - Beautification Drive, Undated
  - Sideburn Civic Association - Berry Associates, 1980-1986
  - Sideburn Civic Association - Budget, 1978
  - Sideburn Civic Association - Bylaws, Undated
  - Sideburn Civic Association - Original Bylaws, Undated
  - Sideburn Civic Association - Correspondence, 1973-1986
  - Sideburn Civic Association - David R. Pinn Memorial Civic & Recreation Center, 1972-1986
  - Sideburn Civic Association - Fairfax County Department of Housing & Community Development Funding, 1974-1983
  - Sideburn Civic Association - Goins Manor, 1979-1983
  - Sideburn Civic Association - History, 1963, 1987
  - Sideburn Civic Association - Letterhead, Undated
  - Sideburn Civic Association - Maps and Plans, 1973-1974
  - Sideburn Civic Association - Meetings, 1974, 1981-1982
  - Sideburn Civic Association - National Committee on Self-Development of People, 1979
  - Sideburn Civic Association - Rezoning Application RZ 80-A-004, 1980-1981
  - Sideburn Civic Association - Saunders B. Moon Housing Development Corporation, 1982-1983
  - Sideburn Civic Association - Tax Information, 1973-1981
  - Sideburn Civic Association - Testimonies and Presentations, 1973-1983
  - Sideburn Civic Association - Treasurer's Report, 1974
  - Sideburn Civic Association - Turkey Shoot Permits, 1975
  - Sideburn Civic Association - United Communities for Improvement Inc., Undated
  - Sideburn Civic Association - Zion Drive Sewer & Water Service, 1973
- Series 6: Noble Lodge No. 9627 Grand United Order of Odd Fellows of America, 1921-1922
  - Noble Lodge No. 9627 Hall Fundraising at Sideburn, Va., 1921-1922
- Series 7: Church Activities, 1956-2016
  - Funeral Programs (1 of 2), 1987-2011
  - Funeral Programs (2 of 2), 1985-2009
  - Greater Little Zion Baptist Church - Church Directory, 1986
  - Greater Little Zion Baptist Church - Church Directory, 1991
  - Greater Little Zion Baptist Church - Church Directory, 2002
  - Greater Little Zion Baptist Church - History, 1964-2016
  - Greater Little Zion Baptist Church - Newspaper clippings, 1987-1997
  - Greater Little Zion Baptist Church - Program booklet - 101st Anniversary Celebration, 1992
  - Greater Little Zion Baptist Church - Program booklet - 102nd Anniversary Celebration, 1993
  - Greater Little Zion Baptist Church - Program booklet - 125th Anniversary Celebration, 2016
  - Greater Little Zion Baptist Church - Program booklet - Rev. James D. Peters, Jr. Installation Services, 1956
  - Greater Little Zion Baptist Church - Program booklet - Unveiling Service and Dedication, 1990
  - Mount Calvary Baptist Church - Program booklet -120th Anniversary Celebration, 1990
- Series 8: Publications, 1858-1946
  - A Treasury of Pleasure Books for Young People [Inscribed to Francis P. Mackall and Alexander Mackall], 1858
  - The Crisis A Record of The Darker Races Vol. 22 No. 6, 1921 October
  - Colored Citizens Association Fairfax County, Va. Thirtieth Anniversary, 1941 June 8
  - Negro Digest, 1946 November
- Series 9: Photographs and Albums, 1935-2011
  - Laurence Arnold, Undated
  - Baylor Family, 1949
  - Gilbert Carter, 1957
  - Goins Family Reunion, c. 2004
  - Goins Flag Raising Ceremony - David R. Pinn Community Center, 1991 December 1
  - Goins Manor Groundbreaking and Dedication, 1983-1984
  - Annie V. Goins, 1953-1991
  - James M. Goins, 1957-1979
  - James M. Goins - U.S. Navy Co. X 280 U.S. Naval Training Center, Bainbridge, MD group photo, 1944 October 16
  - Greater Little Zion Baptist Church - 100th Anniversary, 1991
  - Greater Little Zion Baptist Church - Construction on New Sanctuary, 1989-1990
  - Greater Little Zion Baptist Church - Miscellaneous Events, 1978-1996
  - James Lester Hunter, Undated
  - Gloria Hutchenson, Undated
  - Thomas Jeffrey and Mary B. Jeffrey, 1948
  - Thomas Jeffrey/Jackson Goins Parents (possibly Frank Gillingham?), Undated
  - Edward Metcalf, Undated
  - Charles Pearson, Undated
  - Roots Family, Undated
  - Roots Family - Christmas, 1977, 1981
  - Roots Family - House at 10133 Zion Drive, 1974-1981
  - Daphne Roots, Undated, 2002
  - Daphne Roots - Masters Graduation, 2000
  - James B. Roots, 2000
  - James B. Roots and Stephanie Franckowiak Wedding, 2001 March
  - Mary Goins Roots, c. 1940s - 2010
  - Mary Goins Roots - Family Photo Album, c. 1970s
  - Mary Goins Roots - Family Photo Album, Undated, 1998
  - Mary Goins Roots - Family Photo Album, Undated 1988
  - Mary Goins Roots - Family Photo Album - Goins, Jeffrey, Roots family members, Undated
  - Mary Goins Roots - Eva Turner Elementary School [photo album], Undated, 1996
  - Mary Goins Roots - Eva Turner Elementary School [photo album], Undated
  - Mary Goins Roots - Eva Turner Elementary School staff, 1996-2001
  - Mary Goins Roots - Frog Collection, 1993
  - Mary Goins Roots - Graduation from George Mason University, 1977 August 6
  - Mary Goins Roots - Homecoming Queen, 1961 May
  - Mary Goins Roots - John C. Wood Elementary School staff, 1982-1983
  - Mary Goins Roots - NAESP Convention San Francisco, 1991
  - Mary Goins Roots - Retirement from Fairfax County Public Schools, 1994
  - Mary Goins Roots - Retirement from Eva Turner Elementary School, 2001
  - Mary Goins Roots - Saint Paul's College Class of 1961, 1961
  - Mary Goins Roots - Willow Springs Elementary School staff, 1989-1992
  - Mary Goins Roots and William T. Roots, 1961-2004
  - Mary Goins Roots and William T. Roots - Wedding album, 1961
  - Sam Roots, Undated
  - William T. Roots, 1961-c.2000s
  - William T. Roots - Photo scrapbook album, c. 1950s
  - William T. Roots - U.S. Air Force, 1963-1968
  - William T. Roots - U.S. Air Force - Berlin, 1964
  - Schools - Eva Turner Elementary School [watercolor by Ellen Jones], 2001
  - Schools - Greenbriar West Elementary School [watercolor by Ellen Jones], 1989
  - Schools - John C. Wood School [drawing by Jackie Cawley], Undated
  - Schools - Oakview School (Fairfax, VA) class photos, 1977, 1982
  - Schools - Willow Springs School [watercolor by Ellen Jones], 1994
  - Sideburn, VA area, Undated
  - Tops Drive Inn employee (unidentified), Undated
  - Taylor M. Williams - Luther Jackson High School principal, Undated
  - Cynthia Laverne Wilson, Undated
  - Wright Family, 1966-2011
  - Howard Wilson Wright, 1935-1942
  - Unidentified - Baptism ceremony, Undated
  - Unidentified - Children, Undated
  - Unidentified - Children, Undated
  - Unidentified - Couple, Undated
  - Unidentified - Fairfax County government events (Jack Herrity and William S. Hoofnagle), Undated
  - Unidentified - Groups, Undated
  - Unidentified - Men, Undated
  - Unidentified - Military, Undated
  - Unidentified - School scenes, graduations (St. Paul's College and Fairfax County Public Schools), Undated
  - Unidentified - Weddings, Undated
  - Unidentified - Women, Undated